Guide to the Nava Atlas Papers, 1970s-2020 RL.00059
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nava Atlas papers
1970s-2020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Atlas, Nava
RL.00059
12.5 Linear Feet
Fine artist and author of many cookbooks and other works of nonfiction. Collection includes materials from Atlas' dual careers as a fine artist, book artist, and as the author of vegetarian/vegan cookbooks and other works of nonfiction. Includes book proposals, correspondence, proofs and dummies, reviews, and promotional pieces from many of Atlas' published works, as well as artwork, articles, and drafts from various freelance pieces. Also contains a number of slides of Atlas' early artwork, exhibit-related correspondence and files, publisher and agent materials, and other miscellaneous files relating to her works.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Nava Atlas Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012, 2013, 2014, 2017 and 2020.
Biographical and Historical Note
Nava Atlas is an artist and writer who is known both as a fine artist and as a vegetarian cookbook author. Her artists' books engage images, text, and structure to explore themes of social justice and women's roles. Many of her works, like the altered comic book Love & Marriage, reappropriate found materials and challenge the language and images used to reinforce gender roles and stereotypes.
One unusual aspect of Atlas's work is her adaptation of limited edition artist's books to create trade editions, bridging the divide between hand crafted books and conventional publishing. The first, Secret Recipes for the Modern Wife, a parody 1950s-style cookbook exploring contemporary marriage, was published in 2009 by Simon & Schuster; the second, Dear Literary Ladies, was published as a trade edition under the title The Literary Ladies' Guide to the Writing Life in 2011 by Sellers Publishing. This book explores first-person narratives on the writing lives of twelve classic women authors, and comments on the universal relevance of their experiences to all women who love to write.
Atlas is also the author and illustrator of many books on vegan and vegetarian cooking, most recently Vegan Holiday Kitchen, Vegan Express, Vegan Soups and Hearty Stews for All Seasons, The Vegetarian Family Cookbook, and The Vegetarian 5-Ingredient Gourmet. A book on leafy greens, Wild About Greens, will be published in June 2012. Nava also has written scores of articles on healthful cooking with natural foods, which have appeared in Vegetarian Times, VegNews, Cooking Light, and numerous other publications. Her home is in the Hudson Valley region of New York State, where she lives with her husband; they have two grown children.
Visit her websites here: www.navaatlasart.com and www.vegkitchen.com/
Collection Overview
This collection has been sorted into two series, reflecting the presence of materials from Atlas' dual careers as a book artist and as a vegetarian chef and cookbook author. Both series includes book proposals, correspondence, proofs and dummies, reviews, and promotional pieces from many of Atlas' published works, as well as artwork, articles, and drafts from her various freelance pieces. The collection also contains a number of slides of Atlas' early artwork, exhibit-related correspondence and files, publisher and agent materials, and other miscellaneous files relating to her works.
Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Women authors; Man-woman relationships -- Humor; American wit and humor; Romance comic books, strips, etc.; Artists' books; Vegan cooking; Cooking, American; Prescriptive literature; Vegetarianism; Vegetarian cooking; Atlas, Nava; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Artists' Books and Other Projects, 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Series includes a wide range of materials from Atlas' career as a book artist, including files from her trade edition publication of The Literary Ladies' Guide to the Writing Life and Secret Recipes for the Modern Wife. Other publications include Expect the Unexpected When You're Expecting!, Love and Marriage, The Idea Book, and Hand Jobs. Other material in this series relates to her many exhibits, correspondence, installations, travels, and other artwork and illustrations. Oversize material is housed in Box 9.
  - Test prints for various artists' books (Box 6)
  - Friendship with Dorothy Dehner, 1980-1994 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Jennifer Josephy, 2008 (Box 6)
  - Vamp and Tramp artists' books sales, 2008-2011, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous writings and correspondence, 2000-2009 (Box 6)
  - Europe trip, 2006 (Box 6)
  - Artists' book collections, letters (Box 6)
  - 41 Union Square West, 1980s (Box 6)
  - Hand in Hand gallery collaborations and exhibit, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Brooklyn Museum exhibit, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Albany Institute exhibit, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Maryland Humor, Wit... exhibit, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Wichita Art Museum, miscellaneous, 1985 (Box 6)
  - The Radwaste Books series, 1984 (Box 6)
  - In Retrospect, 2010-2011, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Magdelena Laundries: A Cross to Bear photos and research, 2009 (Box 6)
  - Map of the Interior, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Everson, Fit to be Bound, 2010 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Shows, 2007-2011, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Graduate Schools research papers, 2004-2007 (Box 6)
  - Traveling exhibit, Wichita, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Traveling exhibit, SUNY New Paltz, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - Traveling exhibit, SUNY Oswego, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Traveling Visual Arts Program, Kansas, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Slides of older work, 1999-2006, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous brochures and announcements for traveling exhibit In Retrospect and others, 2010-2013 (Box 11)
  - Freelance book covers, 1977-1980 (Box 12)
  - Art New England July/August 2013 feature article on artist's books (Box 12)
  - The Literary Ladies' Guide to the Writing Life (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 7)
    - Rejection letters, 2009 (Box 7)
    - Writeup and catalog pages (Box 7)
    - Proposal, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Uncorrected proofs (Box 7)
    - 1st pass (Box 8)
    - 2nd pass (Box 8)
    - Oversize proofs (Box 9)
    - Benjamin Franklin Awards brochure, 2012 (Box 11)
    - First version, 2007 (Box 11)
  - Secret Recipes for the Modern Wife (Box 7)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Proposal (Box 7)
    - Selected Reviews and Interviews, 2009, 1 PDF, 5.15 MB
      [PDF file has been transferred to Library Server and can be accessed in the reading room]
    - Trade edition reviews and promotions, 2009, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Trade edition mail and email, 2007-2009, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Oversize test pages (Box 9)
    - Test print for installation (Box 11)
  - Love and Marriage (Box 7)
    - Materials (Box 7)
    - Oversize enlargements (Box 9)
  - Any Man Gets Tired of Toast All the Time, 2008, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Tomcats and Trollops dummy (Box 9)
  - Sluts and Studs dummy (Box 9)
  - Prints (Box 9)
  - In Retrospect large prints (Box 9)
  - Modern Romance Comix, 2009-2010 (Box 7)
  - Hand Jobs, 2009 (Box 7)
    - Test pages (Box 7)
    - Oversize test pages (Box 9)
    - Test prints, 2008 (Box 11)
  - The Idea Book (Box 8)
    - Cover graphics (Box 8)
    - Oversize cover proofs (Box 9)
  - Expect the Unexpected When You're Expecting! (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Press and reviews (Box 5)
    - What To Expect press (Box 5)
    - Radio tour (Box 5)
    - Galleys (Box 5)
    - Illustrations (Box 8)
    - Book cover mounted on foam core (Box 13)
  - Why You Can't Get Married, 2013 (Box 10)
    - First printer's proof, with errors (Box 10)
    - Page proofs (Box 10)
    - Dummy copy (Box 10)
    - Second printer's proof (Box 10)
  - The Art of the Animal: Fourteen Women Artists Explore The Sexual Politics of Meat, 2015 (Box 14)
    Scope and Contents
    The folder consists of the artists'book entitled The Art of the Animal: Fourteen Women Artists Explore The Sexual Politics of Meat, edited by Kathryn Eddy, L.A. Watson, and Janell O'Rourke. The book was published by Lantern Books in 2015. It contains an excerpt from Nava Atlas entitled "Deconstructing Elsie."
  - Exhibit Programs, 2014-2016 (Box 14)
  - Sexual Politics of Meat Exhibit, 2017 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Exhibits, 2014-2016 (Box 14)
  - Publicity, 1984-2015 (Box 15)
  - Events, 2013 (Box 15)
  - Book Proposals, 1986-2016 (Box 16)
  - Exhibits, 1986-2016 (Box 16)
  - Stream of Flame, 1980-1984 (Box 16)
  - Creating a Marriage You'll Love, 2010 (Box 16)
  - Research Files on Victorian Era, 1970s-1980 (Box 17)
  - Walter and Poppy, unpublished manuscript, 2016 (Box 20)
  - Printer's Proofs for Artists' Books, 2016-2020 (Box 21)
- Cookbooks and Food Writing, 8 boxes
  Series consists largely of materials surrounding Atlas' career as a food writer, including proposals, correspondence, proofs, and reviews from many of her vegetarian and vegan cookbooks. Also includes agent correspondence, exhibit and promotional materials, and some artwork from selected publications. Oversize material is housed in Box 9.
  - Vegetariana (Box 1)
    - Original proposal, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Permissions letters received, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Exhibit: Arnold Klein Gallery, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Exhibit: Dorsky Gallery, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Flyers, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Library reviews, 1984 (Box 1)
    - First Edition promotion, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Reviews and articles, Detroit area, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Reviews and articles, miscellaneous newspapers, 1984 (Box 1)
    - QBP and Book of the Month Club, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Reviews and articles, miscellaneous magazines, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Cooking and Crafts Club, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Exhibit: Wichita Art Museum, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Reviews and articles, local upstate area, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Proposal, updated and revised (Box 1)
    - Exhibits, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Second Edition, Book Clubs, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Second Edition, Meat Out articles, 1994-1997 (Box 1)
    - Reviews, new edition, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Third Edition, promotion, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Original manuscript, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Oversize artwork (Box 9)
    - Reviews and articles, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Cover mounted on foam core (Box 13)
  - Agents (Box 2)
    - Lisa Ekus (Box 2)
    - Pat Connolley, 1993 and 1996 (Box 2)
    - Susan Schulman, 1997-1999 (Box 2)
  - American Harvest (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Cover (Box 2)
    - Permissions letters (Box 2)
    - Proposal (Box 2)
    - Reprint (Box 2)
    - Reviews and articles, local upstate papers (Box 2)
    - Reviews and articles, magazines (Box 2)
    - Reviews and articles, newspapers (Box 2)
  - Soups (Box 2)
    - CIP and copyright (Box 2)
    - First Edition, Clubs and Catalogs (Box 2)
    - Reviews (Box 2)
  - Vegan Soups (Box 2)
    - Fourth Edition, Photo proofs and reviews (Box 2)
    - Vegetarian Soups (Box 2)
      - Third Edition, Reviews (Box 2)
      - Fourth Edition, Reviews (Box 2)
      - New edition promotion (Box 2)
      - Reviews, new edition (Box 2)
  - Great American Vegetarian (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Promotional materials (Box 2)
    - Proposal (Box 2)
    - Reviews, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Vegetarian 5 Ingredient Gourmet (Box 3)
    - Book Clubs (Box 3)
    - Publicity (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Vegetarian Celebrations (Box 3)
    - Proposal (Box 3)
    - Holiday articles, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - Blurbs and notices (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - New edition, advertisements and promotions (Box 3)
    - New edition, electronic media (Box 3)
    - New edition, newspaper coverage (Box 3)
    - Reviews (Box 3)
    - Rights reversion (Box 3)
  - Vegetarian Family (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Cover (Box 3)
    - Press clips (Box 3)
    - Promotions (Box 3)
    - Proposal (Box 3)
  - Vegan Express (Box 3)
    - Fan mail (Box 3)
    - Blog posts (Box 3)
    - Proposal (Box 3)
    - Press releases (Box 3)
    - Reviews (Box 3)
  - Vegetarian Express (Box 3)
    - Proposal, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Freelance Food Articles (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Cookbook Materials (Box 5)
    - Cookbook fan mail, 2008-2009 (Box 5)
    - Website write ups (Box 5)
    - Website email (Box 5)
    - Amberwood Press (Box 5)
    - Freelance illustration and design, 1976-1980s, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Two articles, 2005-2011 (Box 11)
    - Binder with cookbook reviews and articles, 2001-2007 (Box 13)
    - Early book covers mounted on foam core (Box 13)
      - Vegetarian Family Cookbook (Box 13)
      - Vegetarian Soups For All Seasons (Box 13)
      - Vegetarian Celebrations (Box 13)
      - American Harvest (Box 13)
      - Soups For All Seasons (Box 13)
  - Publicity, 1984-2015 (Box 15)
  - Vegetariana Materials, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Events, 2013 (Box 15)
  - Cookbook Materials, 1984-2015 (Box 15)
  - 5-Ingredient Vegan, 2019 (Box 18)
  - Vegan on a Budget, 2020 (Box 18)
  - Whole Earth Cookbook, annotated, 1972 (Box 19)
  - Printer's Proofs for Plant-Powered Protein, 2020 (Box 21)